Chapter 16.
I both wished and feared to see Mr. Rochester
on the day which followed this sleepless night.
I wanted to hear his voice again, yet feared to meet his eye.
During the early part of the morning, I momentarily expected his coming.
He was not in the frequent habit of entering the school room.
But he did step in for a few minutes sometimes.
And I had the impression that he was sure to visit it that day.
But the morning passed just as usual.
Nothing happened to interrupt the quiet course of Adele's studies.
Only soon after breakfast, I heard some bustle in the neighborhood of Mr.
Rochester's chamber, Mrs. Fairfax's voice
and liars and the cooks, that is John's wife.
And even John's own gruff tones, there were exclamations
of what a mercy master was not burned in his bed.
It is always dangerous to keep a candle lit at night.
How providential that he had presence of mind to think of the water jug.
I wonder he waked nobody.
It is to be hoped he will not take cold with sleeping on the library sofa, etc.
To much confabulation succeeded a sound of scrubbing and setting to rights.
And when I passed the room in going downstairs to dinner, I saw through the
open door that awe was again restored to complete order.
Only the bed was stripped of its hangings.
Lea stood up in the window seat, rubbing the pains of glass dimmed with smoke.
I was about to address her, for I wished to
know what account had been given of the affair.
But on advancing, I saw a second person in the chamber, a woman sitting on a chair by
the bedside and sowing rings to new curtains.
That woman was no other than grace pool.
There she sat, stayed and taciturn looking, as usual, in her brown stuffed
gown, her check apron, white and couchiff and cap.
She was intent on her work, in which her whole thoughts seemed absorbed.
On her hard forehead, and in her commonplace features, was nothing either
of the paleness or desperation, one would have expected to see marking the
countenance of a woman who had attempted murder, and whose
intended victim had followed her last night to her lair.
And, as I believed, charged her with the crime she wished to perpetrate.
I was amazed, confounded, she looked up, while I still gazed at her, no start,
no increase or failure of color, betrayed emotion, consciousness of guilt
or fear of detection.
She said, good morning, miss, in her usual I will put her to some test, thought I.
Such absolute impenetrability is past comprehension.
Good morning, grace, I said.
Has anything happened here?
I thought I heard the servants all talking together a while ago.
Only master had been reading in his bed last night.
He fell asleep with his candle lit, and the curtains got on fire.
But, fortunately, he awoke before the bedclothes or the woodwork caught and
contrived to quench the flames with the water in the ure.
A strange affair, I said, in a low voice, then looking at her fixedly, did Mr.
Rochester wake nobody?
Did no one hear him move?
She again raised her eyes to me, and this time there
was something of consciousness in their expression.
She seemed to examine me wearily, then she answered.
The servants sleep so far off, you know, miss.
They would not be likely to hear.
Mrs. Fairfax room, and yours are the nearest to masters, but Mrs.
Fairfax said she heard nothing.
When people get elderly, they often sleep heavy, she paused, and then added with a
sort of assumed indifference, but still in a marked and significant tone.
But you are young, miss, and I should say a light sleeper.
Perhaps you may have heard a noise.
I did, said I, dropping my voice, so that Leah, who was still polishing the
pains, could not hear me, and at first I thought it was pilot.
But pilot cannot laugh.
And I am certain I heard a laugh and a strange one.
She took a new needle full of thread, waxed it carefully, threaded her needle
with a steady hand, and then observed with perfect composure.
It is hardly likely master would laugh.
I should think, miss, when he was in such danger.
You must have been dreaming.
I was not dreaming, I said, with some warmth, for her brazen coolness provoked me.
Again, she looked at me, and with the same scrutinizing and conscious eye.
Have you told master that you heard a laugh?
She inquired.
I have not had the opportunity of speaking to him this morning.
You did not think of opening your door and looking out into the gallery?
She further asked.
She appeared to be cross questioning me,
attempting to draw from me information unawares.
The idea struck me, that if she discovered I knew or suspected her guilt,
she would be playing of some of her malignant pranks on me.
I thought it advisable to be on my guard.
On the contrary, said I, I bolted my door.
Then you are not in the habit of bolting your
door every night before you get into bed.
Fiend, she wants to know my habits that she may lay her plans accordingly.
Indignation again prevailed over prudence.
I replied sharply.
Hither too, I have often omitted to fasten the bolt.
I did not think it necessary.
I was not aware any danger or annoyance was to be dreaded at Thornfield Hall.
But in future, and I laid marked stress on the words, I shall
take good care to make all secure before I venture to lie down.
It will be wise so to do was her answer.
This neighborhood is as quiet as any I know, and I never heard
of the hall being attempted by robbers since it was a house.
Though there are hundreds of pounds worth of
plate in the plate closet, as is well known.
And you see, for such a large house, there are very
few servants, because master has never lived here much.
And when he does come, being a bachelor, he needs little waiting on.
But I always think it best to err on the safe side.
A door is soon fastened, and it is as well to have a
drawn bolt between one and any mischief that may be about.
A deal of people miss are for trusting all to providence, but I say providence will
not dispense with the means, though he often
blesses them when they are used discreetly.
And here she closed her rang, a long one for her,
and uttered with the demureness of a quakerus.
I still stood absolutely dumbfounded at what appeared to me, her miraculous self
-possession, and most inscrutable hypocrisy when the cook entered.
Mrs. Paul said she, addressing grace.
The servants dinner will soon be ready.
Will you come down?
No, just put my pint of porter in bit of
pudding on a tray, and I'll carry it upstairs.
You'll have some meat?
Just a morsel and a taste of cheese, that's all.
And the sargo?
Never minded at present.
I shall be coming down before tea time.
I'll make it myself.
The cook here turned to me, saying that Mrs. Fairfax was waiting for me,
so I departed.
I hardly heard Mrs. Fairfax's account of the curtain conflagration during dinner.
So much was I occupied in puzzling my brains over the enigmatical character of
Grace Paul, and still more in pondering the problem of her position at Thornfield,
and questioning why she had not been given into custody that morning, or,
at the very least, dismissed from her master's service.
He had almost as much as declared his conviction of her criminality last night.
What mysterious cause withheld him from accusing her?
Why had he enjoined me to, to secrecy?
It was strange.
A bold, vindictive and haughty gentleman seemed somehow
in the power of one of the meanest of his dependence.
So much in her power that even when she lifted her hand against his life,
he dared not openly charge her with the attempt, much less punish her for it.
Had Grace been young and handsome, I should have been tempted to think that
tender of feelings than prudence or fear influenced Mr. Rochester in her behalf.
But, hard favored and matronly as she was, the idea could not be admitted.
Yet, I reflected, she has been young once.
Her youth would be contemporary with her masters.
Mrs. Fairfax told me once she had lived here many years.
I don't think she can ever have been pretty.
But, for what I know, she may possess originality and strength of character to
compensate for the want of personal advantages.
Mr. Rochester is an amateur of the decided and eccentric.
Grace is eccentric at least.
What if a former Caprice, a freak very possible to a nature so sudden and
headstrong as his, has delivered him into her power, and she now exercises over his
actions a secret influence, the result of his own
indiscretion, which he cannot shake off and dare not disregard.
But, having reached this point of conjecture, Mrs. Poole's square,
flat figure and uncumly, dry even coarse face, occurred so distinctly to my mind's
eye, that I thought, no, impossible, my supposition cannot be correct.
Yet, suggested the secret voice which talks to us in our own hearts,
you are not beautiful either.
And perhaps, Mr. Rochester approves you.
At any rate, you have often felt as if he did.
And last night, remember his words, remember his look, remember his voice.
I well remembered all, language, glance, and
tone seemed at the moment vividly renewed.
I was now in the schoolroom, Adele was drawing.
I bent over her and directed her pencil.
She looked up with a sort of start.
I am hot Adele with stooping.
She went on sketching.
I went on thinking.
I hastened to drive from my mind.
The hateful notion I had been conceiving, respecting Grace Poole, it disgusted me.
I compared myself with her and found we were different.
Bessie Levin had said I was quite a lady, and she spoke truth.
I was a lady, and now I looked much better than I did when Bessie saw me.
I had more color and more flesh, more life, more vivacity,
because I had brighter hopes and keener enjoyments.
Evening approaches said I, as I looked towards the window.
I have never heard Mr. Rochester's voice or step in the
house today, but surely I shall see him before night.
I feared the meeting in the morning.
Now I desire it, because expectation has been
so long baffled that it is grown impatient.
When dusk actually closed, and when Adele left me to go and
play in the nursery with Sophie, I did most keenly desire it.
I listened for the bell to ring below.
I listened for Lea coming up with a message.
I fancied sometimes I heard Mr. Rochester's own tread, and
I turned to the door, expecting it to open and admit him.
The door remained shut.
Darkness only came in through the window.
Still, it was not late.
He often sent for me at seven and eight o 'clock, and it was yet but six.
Surely I should not be wholly disappointed
tonight, when I had so many things to say to him.
I wanted again to introduce the subject of
Grace Pool, and to hear what he would answer.
I wanted to ask him plainly if he really believed it was she who had made last
night's hideous attempt, and if so, why he kept her wickedness a secret.
It little mattered whether my curiosity irritated him.
I knew the pleasure of vexing and soothing him by turns.
It was one I chiefly delighted in, and a sure
instinct always prevented me from going too far.
Beyond the verge of provocation, I never ventured.
On the extreme brink, I liked well to try my skill, retaining
every minute form of respect, every propriety of my station.
I could still meet him in argument without fear or uneasy restraint.
This suited both him and me.
A tread creaked on the stairs at last.
Lea made her appearance, but it was only to intimate that tea was ready in Mrs.
Fairfax's room.
Vither I repaired, glad at least to go downstairs, for that brought me,
I imagined, nearer to Mr. Rochester's presence.
You must want your tea, said the good lady, as I joined her.
You ate so little at dinner.
I am afraid, she continued.
You are not well today.
You look flushed and feverish.
Oh, quite well, I never felt better.
Then you must prove it by evinsing a good appetite.
Will you fill the teapot while I knit off this needle?
Having completed her task, she rose to draw down the blind, which she had
hitherto kept up, by way I suppose, of making the most of daylight.
The dusk was now fast-deepening into total obscurity.
It is fair tonight, said she, as she looked through the pains, though not starlight.
Mr. Rochester has, on the whole, had a favourable day for his journey.
Journey?
Is Mr. Rochester gone anywhere?
I did not know he was out.
Oh, he set off the moment he had breakfasted.
He has gone to the knees, Mr. Eston's place, ten miles on the other side, Millcoat.
I believe there is quite a party assembled there.
Lord Ingram, Sir George Lynn, Colonel Dent, and others.
Do you expect him back tonight?
No.
Nor tomorrow, either.
I should think he is very likely to stay a week or more.
When these fine, fashionable people get together, they are so surrounded by
elegance and gayity, so well-provided with all that complies and entertain,
they are in no hurry to separate.
Gentlemen, especially, are often in request on such occasions, and Mr.
Rochester is so talented and so lively in
society, that I believe he is a general favourite.
The ladies are very fond of him, though you would not think his appearance
calculated to recommend him particularly in their eyes.
But I suppose his requirements and abilities, perhaps his wealth and good
blood, make amends for any little fault of look.
Are there ladies at the knees?
There are Mrs. Eston and her three daughters, very elegant young ladies, indeed.
And there are the honourable blanche and Mary Ingram, most beautiful women,
I suppose.
Indeed, I have seen blanche six or seven
years since, when she was a girl of eighteen.
She came here to a Christmas ball and party Mr. Rochester gave.
You should have seen the dining room that day, how richly it was decorated,
how brilliantly lit up.
I should think there were fifty ladies and gentlemen present, all of the first county
families, and Mrs. Ingram was considered the bell of the evening.
You saw her?
You say Mrs. Fairfax, what was she like?
Yes, I saw her.
The dining room doors were thrown open, and, as it was Christmas time,
the servants were allowed to assemble in the
hall to hear some of the ladies sing and play.
Mr. Rochester would have me to come in, and I
sat down in a quiet corner and watched them.
I never saw a more splendid scene.
The ladies were magnificently dressed, most of them.
At least most of the younger ones looked
handsome, but Mrs. Ingram was certainly the queen.
And what was she like?
Tall, fine bust, sloping shoulders, long, graceful neck, olive complexion dark
and clear, noble features, eyes rather like Mr. Rochester's, large and black,
and as brilliant as her jewels.
And then, she had such a fine head of hair, raven black and so becomingly arranged.
A crown of thick plates behind, and in front
the longest, the glossiest curls I ever saw.
She was dressed in pure white.
An amber-colored scarf was passed over her shoulder and across her breast,
tied at the side, and descending in long, fringed ends below her knee.
She wore an amber-colored flower too, in her hair.
It contrasted well with the jetty mass of her curls.
She was greatly admired, of course.
Yes, indeed.
And not only for her beauty, but for her accomplishments.
She was one of the ladies who sang.
A gentleman accompanied her on the piano.
She and Mr. Rochester sang a duet.
Mr. Rochester, I was not aware he could sing.
Oh, he has a fine bass voice and an excellent taste for music.
And Miss Ingram, what sort of a voice had she?
A very rich and powerful one.
She sang delightfully.
It was a treat to listen to her, and she played afterwards.
I am no judge of music, but Mr. Rochester is.
And I heard him say her execution was remarkably good.
And this beautiful and accomplished lady, she is not yet married.
It appears not.
I fancy neither she nor her sister have very large fortunes.
Old Lord Ingram's estates were chiefly entailed,
and the elder son came in for everything almost.
But I wonder no wealthy nobleman or gentleman has taken a fancy to her.
Mr. Rochester, for instance.
He is rich, is he not?
Oh, yes.
But you see there is a considerable difference in age.
Mr. Rochester is nearly 40.
She is but 25.
What of that?
More unequal matches are made every day.
True.
Yet I should scarcely fancy Mr. Rochester would entertain an idea of the sort.
But you eat nothing.
You have scarcely tasted since you began tea.
No, I am too thirsty to eat.
Will you let me have another cup?
I was about again to revert to the probability of a union between Mr.
Rochester and the beautiful blanche.
But a del came in and the conversation was turned into another channel.
When once more alone, I reviewed the information I had got, looked into my
heart, examined its thoughts and feelings, and endeavored to bring back with a strict
hand such as had been straining through imaginations boundless and trackless waste
into the safe fold of common sense.
Arrained at my own bar, memory having given her evidence of the hopes,
wishes, sentiments I had been cherishing since last night.
Of the general state of mind, in which I had indulged for nearly a fortnight past,
reason haven't come forward and told in her own quiet way a plain unvarnished
tale, showing how I had rejected the real and rapidly devoured the ideal.
I pronounced judgment to this effect, that a greater fool than Jane Eyre had
never breathed the breath of life, that a more fantastic idiot had never
surfated herself on sweet lies and swallowed poison as if it were nectar.
You, I said, a favourite with Mr. Rochester, you gifted with the power of
pleasing him, you of importance to him in any way?
Go, your folly sickened me, and you have derived pleasure from occasional tokens of
preference, equivocal tokens shown by a gentleman of
family and a man of the world, to a dependent and a novice.
How dared you?
Poor stupid dupe, could not even self -interest make you wiser.
You repeated to yourself this morning the brief scene of last night.
Cover your face and be ashamed.
He said something in praise of your eyes, did he?
Blind puppy, open their bled lids and look on your own accursed senselessness.
It does good to no woman to be flattered by her superior, who cannot possibly
intend to marry her, and it is madness in all women, to let a secret love kindle
within them, which, if unreturned and unknown, must devour the life that feeds
it, and, if discovered and responded to, must lead, igneus,
fatuous, like into myriwilds once there is no extrication.
Listen then, Jane Eyre, to your sentence.
Tomorrow, place the glass before you, and draw in chalk your own picture,
faithfully, without softening one defect, omit no harsh line, smooth away no
displeasing irregularity, right under it, portrait
of a governess disconnected poor and plain.
Afterwards, take a piece of smooth ivory.
You have one prepared in your drawing box.
Take your palette, mix your freshest, finest, clearest tints, choose your most
delicate camelhair pencils, delineate carefully the loveliest face you can
imagine, paint it in your softer shades and sweetest lines, according to the
description given by Mrs. Fairfax of Blanche Ingram.
Remember the raven ringlets, the oriental eye.
What, you revert to Mr. Rochester as a model, order, no snivel, no sentiment,
no regret, I will endure only sense and resolution.
Recall the august, yet harmonious lineaments, the greekian neck and bust,
let the round and dazzling arm be visible, and the delicate hand, omit neither
diamond ring nor gold bracelet, portray faithfully the attire,
aerial lace and glistening satin, graceful scarf and golden rose,
call its Blanche, an accomplished lady of rank.
Whenever in future you should chance to fancy Mr. Rochester thinks well of you,
take out these two pictures and compare them, say.
Mr. Rochester might probably win that noble lady's love if he chose to strive for it.
Is it likely he would waste a serious thought
on this indigent and insignificant plebeian?
I'll do it, I resolved, and having framed this
determination, I grew calm and fell asleep.
I kept my word, an hour or two sufficed to sketch my own portrait in crayons,
and in less than a fortnight I had completed an
ivory miniature of an imaginary Blanche Ingram.
It looked a lovely face enough, and when compared with the real head in
chalk, the contrast was as great as self -control could desire.
I derived benefit from the task.
It had kept my head and hands employed and had given force and fix itness to the new
impressions I wished to stamp indelibly on my heart.
Air long, I had reason to congratulate myself on the course of wholesome
discipline to which I had thus forced my feelings to submit.
Thanks to it, I was able to meet subsequent occurrences with a decent calm,
which had they found me unprepared, I should probably
have been unequal to maintain, even externally.